Guide to the Benedicion Santa Ana de Branconière: Lecture notes taken by Josephine Robinson, 1906-1910
Department of Special Collections
Branconière, Benedicion Santa Ana de. Lecture notes taken by Josephine Robinson,
1906-1910
M1112
Branconière, Benedicion Santa Ana de.
8 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Biography
Miss Benedicion Santa Ana de Branconiere was born the daughter of a British nobleman during the 18th century. Her father was a well-read and educated man, and at the time was the owner of one of the finest private libraries in the world. At a fairly young age, Miss de Branconiere was found to suffer from tuberculosis of the bone. After English medical science failed to cure her, Miss de Branconiere set out with her father to search the world for treatment. They finally found help in India, from spiritual healer and great religious figure Swami Vivekananda. To display her gratification for his assistance, Miss de Branconiere began to study under Swami Vivekananda in the hope of one day helping to spread his word to the western world. His doctrine was one of bringing together people of all religions to recognize that the God they worshiped was one. At the conference of World Religions held in Chicago in 1893, he said "People born in different religions finally reach the same God, as rivers born in different places finally reach the sea." To carry out her promise, Miss de Branconiere studied at the School of Illumination in Paris (Brotherhood of Light), where she later taught. After her tenure there, Swami Vivekananda sent her to spread the word, as he had briefly, in still-developing America. Miss de Branconiere acquiring a position at the University of California, Berkeley, teaching religion, philosophy, and literature. She also instructed evening classes to a private study group in Alameda. Through her teachings, Miss de Branconiere examined the sacred books of the world's four great religions, as well as the classic literary works of the time, seeking what common truths they held that could assist the plight of man. The central point of her teachings, as is any serious pursuit of the truth, was the discovery and salvation of the individual human soul.
Scope and Content
This collection contains transcripts of the lectures Miss de Branconiere gave from 1906 through 1910. Josephine Robinson, then employed by the Bank of Alameda, attended her evening sessions, took notes in shorthand, and typed them later. The collection fills sixteen manuscript boxes and is organized chronologically. The collection includes two indexes: one that provides dates for lectures in which certain topics were discussed, and a second, which exclusively pertains to Biblical references. The lectures given by Miss de Branconiere cover a wide variety of religious and philosophical issues, while citing sources that range from classic Greek myths to Shakespeare to major religious texts. Miss de Branconiere quotes Swami Vivekananda extensively in her teachings, and students of the Swami should find great interest in the lectures of his disciple and protégée, Miss de Branconiere.
Access Terms
Vivekananda, Swami, 1863-1902.; Robinson, Josephine.; Hinduism.; Hindus--India.; Philosophy.; Religion.; Vedanta.; Lecture notes.
Collection Contents
- St. John7/11/1906-8/15/1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- St. John8/19/1906-9/21/1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Science9/16/1906-10/2/1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Science10/5/1906-10/24/1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Exodus10/24/1906-12/5/1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Exodus10/2/1906-10/28/1906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Exodus11/4/1906-12/16/1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Exodus2/10/1907-2/26/1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Genesis11/21/1906-12/29/1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Genesis1/31/1907-2/28/1907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Virtue12/12/1906-2/17/1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Virtue2/13/1907-2/27/1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Psalms1/7/1907-1/29/1907 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Psalms2/6/1907-4/8/1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- David3/1/1907-4/12/1907 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- David3/3/1907-3/20/1907 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Virtue II3/24/1907-4/14/1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Virtue II4/17/1907-4/28/1907 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Virtue II5/1/1907-6/5/1907 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Virtue II6/2/1907-6/9/1907 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Exodus3/5/1907-3/19/1907 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Exodus3/26/1907-4/16/1907 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Exodus4/23/1907-4/30/1907 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Genesis (Hand Written)11/21/1906-5/2/1907 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Genesis3/7/1907-3/28/1907 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Genesis4/4/1907-5/2/1907 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Genesis5/9/1907-5/23/1907 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Exodus5/10/1907-5/28/1907 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Exodus6/4/1907-6/18/1907 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Exodus6/25/1907-9/3/1907 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Exodus9/17/1907-12/16/1907 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Genesis II6/3/1907-6/13/1907 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Genesis II6/20/1907-8/23/1907 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Genesis II9/1/1907-9/19/1907 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Evasion: Volitive Latency 6/2/1907-6/19/1907 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Evasion: Volitive Latency6/23/1907-8/25/1907 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Evasion: Volitive Latency9/4/1907-9/15/1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Evasion: Volitive Latency9/18/1907-10/2/1907 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Evasion: Volitive Latency10/9/1907-10/29/1907 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Omar8/25/1907-9/8/1907 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Omar9/15/1907-10/13/1907 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Omar10/13/1907-12/15/1907 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Omar12/15/1907-1/12/1908 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Meditation1/7/1908-1/12/1908 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Meditation1/13/1908-1/15/1908 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Meditation1/16/1908-1/19/1908 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Meditation1/20/1908-1/23/1908 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Hamlet1/26/1908 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Hamlet1/28/1908-1/30/1908 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Merchant of Venice & Othello2/23/1908-3/1/1908 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Macbeth3/22/1908 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Peacock Plume & Minerva2/9/1908-3/8/1908 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Bellerophon3/29/1908 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Aristaeus5/10/1908-5/17/1908 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Orpheus & Eurydice1/14/1909-1/24/1909 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Proserpine & Pluto2/16/1908 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Cupid & Psyche3/15/1908 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Hercules4/12/1908-5/3/1908 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Nemesis & Golden Fleece5/24/1908-6/7/1908 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Sister Helen, Medusa & Perseus6/19/1908-7/12/1908 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Meditation2/2/1908-2/4/1908 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Meditation2/5/1908-2/11/1908 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Meditation2/12/1908-2/18/1908 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Meditation2/19/1908-2/27/1908 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Meditation3/2/1908-3/10/1908 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Meditation3/11/1908-3/18/1908 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Meditation3/19/1908-3/31/1908 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Meditation4/1/1908-4/19/1908 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Meditation4/20/1908-4/22/1908 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Meditation4/27/1908-4/29/1908 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Meditation4/9/1908-4/23/1908 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Meditation5/7/1908-7/9/1908 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Exodus5/28/1908-6/2/1908 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Exodus6/4/1908-6/9/1908 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Meditation5/4/1908-5/12/1908 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Meditation5/13/1908-5/19/1908 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Meditation5/20/1908-5/27/1908 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Meditation6/1/1908-6/8/1908 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Background, Definitions7/13/1908-7/16/1908 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Background, Definitions7/19/1908-7/28/1908 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Background, Definitions7/29/1908-7/30/1908 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Exodus III7/14/1908-7/21/1908 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Exodus III7/23/1908-7/28/1908 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Exodus III7/30/1908-8/6/1908 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Exodus III8/11/1908-8/27/1908 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Preliminary Meditation7/24/1908-7/30/1908 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Preliminary Meditation7/31/1908-8/17/1908 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Ezekiel7/10/1908-7/12/1908 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Ezekiel7/17/1908-7/19/1908 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Ezekiel7/24/1908 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Ezekiel7/27/1908-7/31/1908 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Ezekiel II8/2/1908-8/9/1908 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Ezekiel II8/16/1908-8/26/1908 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Ezekiel II8/27/1908-8/30/1908 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Ezekiel II8/30/1908 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Biology of Creation8/2/1908-8/3/1908 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Biology of Creation8/4/1908-8/5/1908 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Biology of Creation8/6/1908-8/11/1908 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Biology of Creation8/2/1908-9/6/1908 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Nescience and Knowledge10/1/1908-10/4/1908 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Nescience and Knowledge10/15/1908-10/21/1908 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Nescience and Knowledge10/22/1908-10/27/1908 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Nescience and Knowledge10/28/1908-10/30/1908 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Hindu Classics10/20/1908 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Hindu Classics7/21/1909 & 3/1/1908 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Hindu Classics3/1/1908-3/7/1908 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Parisfal10/18/1908-10/25/1909 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Parisfal11/1/1908-11/15/1908 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Parisfal11/29/1908-12/13/1908 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Knowledge & Consciousness11/2/1908-11/3/1908 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Knowledge & Consciousness11/4/1908-11/10/1908 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Knowledge & Consciousness11/11/1908-11/18/1908 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Knowledge & Consciousness11/23/1908-11/30/1908 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Knowledge & Consciousness11/10/1908-11/24/1908 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Knowledge12/7/1908-12/14/1908 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Knowledge12/15/1908 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Knowledge12/15/1908-12/17/1908 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Knowledge12/17/1908-12/22/1908 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Memory1/7/1909-1/13/1909 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Memory1/19/1909-1/25/1909 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Memory1/26/1909-1/31/1909 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Entity of the Mind1/12/1909-1/21/1909 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Entity of the Mind1/26/1909-1/28/1909 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Body & Recognition2/1/1909-2/9/1909 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Body & Recognition2/10/1909-2/28/1909 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Body & Recognition3/2/1909-3/10/1909 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Le Grande Persone8/22/1909-8/24/1909 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Le Grande Persone8/25/1909-8/31/1909 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Truth9/1/1909-9/4/1909 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Truth9/5/1909-9/8/1909 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Truth9/8/1909-9/22/1909 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- International Lectures9/1/1909-9/29/1909 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- International Lectures10/2/1909-10/27/1909 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Classics9/11/1909-10/28/1909 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Classics11/11/1909-11/13/1909 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Miss Branconiere's Meditation9/15/1909-9/21/1909 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Miss Branconiere's Meditation9/22/1909-9/30/1909 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Consciousness & Creation 10/2/1909-10/4/1909 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Consciousness & Creation10/5/1909-10/7/1909 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Intelligence10/19/1909-10/24/1909 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Intelligence10/25/1909-10/31/1909 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Time and Space 11/1/1909-11/7/1909 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Time and Space11/9/1909-11/10/1909 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Time and Space11/11/1909-11/17/1909 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Lecture Summaries by Date (Box 10, Folder 9)
- A (Box 10, Folder 10)
- A (Box 10, Folder 11)
- A (Box 10, Folder 12)
- B (Box 10, Folder 13)
- B (Box 11, Folder 1)
- B (Box 11, Folder 2)
- C (Box 11, Folder 3)
- C (Box 11, Folder 4)
- C (Box 11, Folder 5)
- C (Box 11, Folder 6)
- C (Box 11, Folder 7)
- D (Box 11, Folder 8)
- D (Box 11, Folder 9)
- D (Box 11, Folder 10)
- E (Box 11, Folder 11)
- E (Box 11, Folder 12)
- E (Box 12, Folder 1)
- F (Box 12, Folder 2)
- F (Box 12, Folder 3)
- G (Box 12, Folder 4)
- G (Box 12, Folder 5)
- G (Box 12, Folder 6)
- H (Box 12, Folder 7)
- H (Box 12, Folder 8)
- I (Box 12, Folder 9)
- I (Box 12, Folder 10)
- I (Box 12, Folder 11)
- I (Box 12, Folder 12)
- I (Box 13, Folder 1)
- J (Box 13, Folder 2)
- K (Box 13, Folder 3)
- K (Box 13, Folder 4)
- L (Box 13, Folder 5)
- M (Box 13, Folder 6)
- M (Box 13, Folder 7)
- M (Box 13, Folder 8)
- M (Box 13, Folder 9)
- N (Box 13, Folder 10)
- N (Box 13, Folder 11)
- N (Box 13, Folder 12)
- N (Box 13, Folder 13)
- P (Box 14, Folder 1)
- P (Box 14, Folder 2)
- P (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Q (Box 14, Folder 4)
- R (Box 14, Folder 5)
- R (Box 14, Folder 6)
- S (Box 14, Folder 7)
- S (Box 14, Folder 8)
- S (Box 14, Folder 9)
- S (Box 14, Folder 10)
- S (Box 14, Folder 11)
- T (Box 14, Folder 12)
- U (Box 15, Folder 1)
- V (Box 15, Folder 2)
- V (Box 15, Folder 3)
- W (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Y (Box 15, Folder 5)
- A-B (The following are an index of Biblical References) (Box 15, Folder 6)
- C (Box 15, Folder 7)
- D (Box 15, Folder 8)
- E (Box 15, Folder 9)
- F (Box 15, Folder 10)
- G (Box 15, Folder 11)
- H (Box 15, Folder 12)
- I (Box 15, Folder 13)
- J (Box 15, Folder 14)
- K (Box 15, Folder 15)
- L (Box 16, Folder 1)
- M (Box 16, Folder 2)
- N-O (Box 16, Folder 3)
- P (Box 16, Folder 4)
- R (Box 16, Folder 5)
- S (Box 16, Folder 6)
- T-V (Box 16, Folder 7)
- W-Z (Box 16, Folder 8)